Finding Aid for the Pamela Gearhart Papers, 1956-1993
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Pamela Gearhart Papers, 1956-1993
Mus. Arc. 33
Gearhart, Pamela
7 boxes (421 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The Pamela Gearhart Papers contain a biographical summary, curriculum vitae, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and programs.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Pamela Gearhart 2007; additions received in 2015 as a gift from the estate of Pamela Gearhart.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Pamela Gearhart (née Gerhart) was born July 21, 1934 in Altoona, Pennsylvania. She began her musical training with her father, violinist and conductor, Russell Gerhart. Russell Gerhart studied violin with Ralph Lewando, Carl Malcherek, Elias Breeskin, and Mischa Mischakoff. He studied conducting with Serge Koussevitsky at the Berkshire Music Center. Gerhart and his wife Martha formed the Gerhart String Ensemble in Altoona, Pennsylvania, which grew into the Altoona Symphony Orchestra. He also served as conductor of the Saint Louis Philharmonic and Huntsville (Alabama) Civic Symphony.
When Pamela Gearhart was fifteen she began five years of study at the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia. Her violin teachers before and after her years at Curtis were Mischa Mischakoff, Joseph Knitzer, Ivan Galamian and Efrem Zimbalist. While at Curtis she performed in the Curtis Orchestra under conductors Alexander Hilsberg and William Smith, and studied chamber music performance with Karen Tuttle and Marcel Tabuteau.
Gearhart was appointed faculty member in the University of Buffalo Music Department in 1957. Initially she was hired as a part-time instructor in violin but eventually assumed other duties, including conducting the university's orchestra and directing the program in chamber music performance. She continued to work at the University at Buffalo until 1975. Pamela Gearhart married fellow University at Buffalo music faculty member Livingston Gearhart in 1955. They were frequent collaborators on programs and projects. Livingston wrote many musical arrangements geared specifically to the pedagogical needs of Pamela's ensembles. Many of these arrangements and compositions survive in the Livingston Gearhart Score Collection.
While in Buffalo Gearhart also served as conductor of the Community Music School of Buffalo's youth orchestra 1959-1977. The membership in the orchestra grew from ten to more than one hundred while she was conductor. Her credentials as a music educator also include work on the faculty at Villa Maria Institute of Music (Buffalo) 1963-1965, serving for six years as Alexander Schneider's assistant for the University at Buffalo's String Institute, numerous positions as guest conductor and judge at music festivals, and director of the Youth Makes Music String Workshop (Huntsville, Alabama). After leaving the University at Buffalo she joined the faculty at Ithaca College where she taught 1975-1993. In 1980 she founded the Ithaca Youth Orchestra. She continued as its conductor until her retirement from Ithaca College. Pamela Gearhart died July 6, 2014 in Rochester, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The Pamela Gearhart Papers contain brief biographical data, including a biographical summary from 1967, and curriculum vitae from 1971. Also included are clippings, programs, and correspondence. Clippings and programs extend from 1956-1982 and reflect Gearhart's work with the Community Music School of Buffalo, the University at Buffalo Orchestra, the Villa Maria Music Institute, her performances as a member of the Buffalo Fine Arts Quartet, and various other performances. One folder contains programs and clippings chiefly about Livingston Gearhart. Two folders contain documents pertaining to the Youth Makes Music String Workshop that was held in Alabama 1972-1981, a string camp established in memory of Russell Gerhart.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
I. Biographical documents
II. Correspondence
III. Newspaper clippings and programs
IV. Youth Makes Music String Workshop documents
V. Additions received after the original processing was completed
VI. Additional correspondence
Container List
- Biographical documents, 1967-1971, I; Folder 1-4
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Biographical summary, 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 001)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1971, 7 leaves (Box 1, Folder 002)
  - Professional profile, 1971, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 003)
  - Profile of University and Community Music School of Buffalo orchestras written by Pamela Gearhart, 1972, 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 004)
- Correspondence, 1962-1993, II; Folder 5-40
  Arranged alphabetically by author's name with a file of Christmas cards at the end.
  - Albrecht, Milton C., 1904-: January 16 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 005)
  - Baird, Jane: May 16 1993, 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 006)
  - Bellissimo, Ruth W. on behalf of the Community Music School of Buffalo: March 26 1972, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 007)
  - Blackhurst, James: May 19 1974, May 16 1975, and July 20 1979, 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 008)
  - Buffalonian, SUNY at Buffalo Yearbook, written by Pamela Vespucci: July 5 1972, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 009)
  - Carlton House Nursing Home (Buffalo, N.Y.), written by Lena Lenar Horowitz: December 5 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 010)
  - Buffalo Area Council of Churches, written by David F. Cox: April 30 1968, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 011)
  - Deutsch, Harry, for the New York State Council on the Arts: December 28 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 012)
  - Foss, Lukas, 1922-2009: March 22 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 013)
  - Glickman, Loren: May 6 1993, 2 leaves; Correspondence from Livingston and Pamela Gearhart to Glickman about a program honoring Alexander Schneider. (Box 1, Folder 014)
  - Haas, Dorothy M.: April 28 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 015)
  - Haasler, George: June 26 1970, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 016)
  - Hay, Bill: March 27 1962, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 017)
  - Henderson, Skitch, 1918-2005: November 23 1966, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 018)
  - Herr, Samuel L., Director of the Community Music School of Buffalo: March 17 1969, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 019)
  - Hutchins, Carleen Maley, for the Catgut Acoustical Society: June 13 1968, July 7 1994, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 020)
  - Kroyt, Sonja: undated, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 021)
  - Levick, Irving: January 16 1967, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 022)
  - Levine, George R.: May 10 1976, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 023)
  - Nagaard, Richard on behalf of the National School Orchestra Association Bulletin: November 18 1972, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 024)
  - Negris, Van C.: February 21 1964, 1 leaf; Letter addressed to Livingston Gearhart. (Box 1, Folder 025)
  - Newell, Frederick, on behalf of the Unitarian Universalist Church of Amherst (New York). Music Committee: February 2 1968, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 026)
  - Niagara County Community College: December 20 1967, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 027)
  - Sapp, Allen, 1922-1999: April 6 1965, 2 leaves; Letter addressed to University at Buffalo administrator, Myles Slatin, regarding report by Pamela Gearhart about the University Orchestra and Community Music School of Buffalo. (Box 1, Folder 028)
  - Schneider, Mischa, 1903-1985: July 12 1973, February 7 1984, May 30 1985, and undated, 5 leaves (Box 1, Folder 029)
    Four postcards (two addressed to Livingston Gearhart) and one letter. One postcard contains information about photographs of Johannes Brahms in Livingston Gearhart's collection of photographs.
  - Schneider, Alexander, 1908-1993: November 17 1981, August 1 1987, July 20 1989, 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 030)
    One letter and postcard addressed to Livingston Gearhart. One letter addressed to Pamela Gearhart.
  - Schulz, Robert F.: May 4 1971, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 031)
  - Schultz, Gertrude, on behalf of the Jewish Center of Buffalo: March 26 1968, 2 leaves (Box 1, Folder 032)
  - Saint Mary's School for the Deaf (Buffalo, N.Y.): November 15 1971, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 033)
    Signed by Sister Nora Letorneau and Sister Virginia Young.
  - Sullivan, J. P. (John Patrick): July 28 1975, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 034)
  - Thacker, Gale W., of Hodge Inc. Florists: May 28 1968, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 035)
  - Thomson, William, 1927-: November 4 1975, February 17 1976, November 9 1976, 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 036)
  - Thompson, Helen M. (Helen Mulford), 1908-, on behalf of the New York Philharmonic: May 10 1972, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 037)
  - Trotter, Herman: July 20 1975, 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 038)
  - Unitarian Universalist Church of Amherst (Amherst, N.Y.): December 16 1968, January 6 1969, November 24 1969, 3 leaves (Box 1, Folder 039)
  - Christmas cards 1966-1973, 14 leaves (Box 1, Folder 040)
    Christmas messages sent to University at Buffalo and Community Music School orchestras from Livingston and Pamela Gearhart.
- Clippings and programs, 1956-1982, III.; Folder 41-349
  Arranged chronologically.
  - May 16 1956-December 1956, 4 folders (Box 1, Folder 041-044)
  - August 5 1957-November 25 1957, 7 folders (Box 1, Folder 045-051)
  - April 15 1958-November 17 1958, 6 folders (Box 1, Folder 052-057)
  - March 11 1959-November 1959, 10 folders (Box 1, Folder 058-067)
  - January 10 1960-December 1960, 9 folders (Box 1, Folder 068-076)
  - January 15 1961-December 18 1961, 7 folders (Box 1, Folder 077-083)
  - January 15 1962-October 17 1962, 10 folders (Box 2, Folder 084-094)
  - January 14 1963-December 1963, 9 folders (Box 2, Folder 095-103)
  - February 1 1964-October 16 1964, 11 folders (Box 2, Folder 104-114)
  - January 17 1965-August 21 1965, 10 folders (Box 2, Folder 115-125)
  - February 1966-December 15 1966, 13 folders (Box 2, Folder 126-138)
  - January 14 1967-December 27 1967, 26 folders (Box 2, Folder 139-164)
  - March 2 1968-December 20 1968, 24 folders (Box 2, Folder 165-188)
  - February 21 1969-December 31 1969, 22 folders (Box 3, Folder 189-210)
  - February 1970-December 14 1970, 21 folders (Box 3, Folder 211-231)
  - March 20 1971-December 10 1971, 15 folders (Box 3, Folder 232-246)
  - February 15 1972-December 15 1972, 23 folders (Box 3, Folder 247-269)
  - January 27 1973-December 9 1973, 29 folders (Box 3, Folder 270-298)
  - January 1974-December 13 1974, 23 folders (Box 4, Folder 299-321)
  - January 26 1975-November 22 1975, 19 folders (Box 4, Folder 322-340)
  - May 23 1979-November 30 1979, 7 folders (Box 4, Folder 341-347)
  - 1982, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 348)
  - January 16 1956-April 17 1959, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 349)
    Clippings of Livingston Gearhart performances and programs.
- Youth Makes Music String Workshop documents, 1972-1981, IV.; Folder 350-351
  Includes financial records of Youth Makes Music, Inc., programs, announcements, clippings, and lists of participants.
  - 1972-1975, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 350)
  - 1976-1981, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 351)
- Additions received after the original processing was completed, 1947-2010, V.; Folder 352-392
  Includes correspondence, clippings, programs, lecture notes, and subject files.
  Arranged into four subseries:
  A. Correspondence
  B. Subject files
  C. Clippings and programs
  D. Lecture and presentation notes
  E. Awards
  - Correspondence to and from Pamela Gearhart, 1952-2010, V.A; Folder 352-377
    Correspondence to Pamela Gearhart unless otherwise indicated.
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent surname.
    - Barrett, Henry: 1975 July 15, 1 item (2 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 352)
    - Black, Margaret: 2006 April 24, 1 item (3 leaves) and 3 photographs (Box 5, Folder 353)
    - Braun, Edith: 1954 June 7, 1 item (1 leaf) (Box 5, Folder 354)
    - Castleman, Heidi: 1991 March 1, 1 item (2 leaves); Written by Gearhart to Castleman. (Box 5, Folder 355)
      Accompanied by Chamber Music America newsletter.
    - Cleveland Institute of Music: 1981 May 11, 1 item (1 leaf); Written by Dean Rhoda Payne. (Box 5, Folder 356)
    - Cornell University. Department of Music: 1981 November 3, 1 item (1 leaf); Written by James Webster. (Box 5, Folder 357)
    - Curtis Institute of Music: 2002 March, 2 items (2 leaves); Written by Anne O'Donnell. (Box 5, Folder 358)
      Accompanied by Curtis Institute of Music alumni newsletter and printouts of Curtis Web pages.
    - Eastman School of Music: 1976-1977, 2 items (2 leaves); Written by Donald Hunsberger. (Box 5, Folder 359)
    - English, H. R.: 1966 March 18, 1966 March 15, 2 items (3 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 360)
      Includes letter from Gearhart to English.
    - Galamian, Judith: 1971-1991, 7 items (Box 5, Folder 361)
      Includes one letter from Ivan Galamian.
    - Gearhart, Livingston: 1959-circa 1993, 1 folder; Letters to and from Livingston Gearhart. (Box 5, Folder 362)
    - Hartt College of Music: 1990 October 13, 1 item (1 leaf); Written by Gearhart to Humbert J. Lucarelli at Hartt College of Music. (Box 5, Folder 363)
    - Ithaca College: 1975-1993, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 364)
      Includes content written by Pamela Gearhart and by various authors on behalf of Ithaca College. Content includes contracts and appointment papers.
    - Ithaca Youth Bureau (Ithaca, N.Y.): 1976, 2 items (6 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 365)
    - Mischakoff, Mischa: 1952, 11 pages of music (Box 5, Folder 366)
      Solo violin part of Violin concerto by Julius Konius, with inscription from violinist Mischa Mischakoff.
    - Moennig, William, II, 1905-1982: 1966-2010, 6 items (Box 5, Folder 367)
      Includes letters written by Wilda Moennig and Pamela Moennig Taplinger.
    - William Moennig and Son: 1966-1981, 11 items (Box 5, Folder 368)
      Appraisals of violins and bows.
    - Oberlin College. Conservatory of Music: 1987-1988, 7 items; Some content written by Pamela Gearhart. (Box 5, Folder 369)
    - Sokoloff, Eleanor: 1989-2002, 3 items (Box 5, Folder 370)
    - Thomas, Sally: 1967 September 16, 1 item (1 leaf) (Box 5, Folder 371)
    - Tuttle, Karen: 1993-2010, 3 items (Box 5, Folder 372)
    - University at Buffalo. Music Department: 1981 February 24, 1 item (1 leaf); Written on behalf of the department by Allen Sigel. (Box 5, Folder 373)
    - Vauclain, Constant: 1990 August 14, 1 item (1 leaf) (Box 5, Folder 374)
    - Waring, Virginia: 1996 July 19, 1 item (3 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 375)
    - Wickstrom, Helene: circa 1976, 1 item (2 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 376)
    - Zimbalist, Mary Louise Curtis Bok: 1952-1955, 5 items (Box 5, Folder 377)
      Includes letter from Efrem Zimbalist to Pamela Gearhart's father, Russell Gerhart.
  - Subject files, 1950-1981, V.B; Folder 378-388
    Subject files and articles compiled by Pamela Gearhart.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Bay Chamber Concerts: circa 1981, 1 item (Box 5, Folder 378)
      About brothers Andrew and Thomas Wolf, founders of the Bay Chamber Concerts in Rockport, Maine.
    - Curtis Institute of Music: 1952-1954, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 379)
      Gearhart's transcriptions of quotations from faculty at Curtis Institute of Music, including Marcel Tabuteau, Alexander Hilsberg, Anne-Marie Soffray, Karen Tuttle, Louis Vyner, and Constant Vauclain.
    - Curtis Institute of Music: 1952-1954, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 380)
      Gearhart's notes from classes in Elements of music taught by Edith Braun, lists of repertoire covered in orchestra by Alexander Hilsberg and William Smith and string class by Marcel Tabuteau
    - Curtis Institute of Music: 1950-1953, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 381)
      Gearhart's notes from her violin lessons with Ivan Galamian and Efrem Zimbalist, and a list of repertoire covered in Karen Tuttle's chamber music classes
    - Galamian, Ivan: 1966-1995, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 382)
    - Galamian, Judith: 2005, 1 item (Box 5, Folder 383)
    - Green, Elizabeth A. H.: 1995, 3 items (Box 5, Folder 384)
    - William Moennig and Son: 1985-2010, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 385)
    - String pedagogy: 1995, 2001, 2 items (Box 5, Folder 386)
      Two articles by Anne Mischakoff Heiles from The Instrumentalist: Essential string markings and Strings: the golden age of string pedagogy.
    - String pedagogy: undated, 1 item (3 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 387)
      Typescript by unidentified author.
    - Tuttle, Karen: 1986-2004, 2 items and 1 photograph (Box 5, Folder 388)
  - Clippings and programs, 1947-1993, V.C; Folder 389
    One binder with contents as received.
    Contents chiefly arranged chronologically.
    - 1947-1993, 1 binder (Box 6, Folder 389)
      Includes clippings about Pamela Gearhart, Chautauqua Institute, Russell Gerhart, the Altoona Symphony Orchestra, and Ithaca College.
  - Lecture and presentation notes, 1962-1980, V.D; Folder 390-395
    Lecture notes
    Arranged as received.
    - Orchestra in action: 1973, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 390)
      Notes for presentation with the Buffalo Community Music School Orchestra.
    - What is a family?: 1970-1976, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 391)
      Notes for presentations with the strings of the University at Buffalo Orchestra (1970) and the Ithaca College String Orchestra (1976).
    - Notes for several speeches and presentations: 1965-1980, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 392)
    - Clinic notes: undated, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 393)
    - Notes for several lectures: undated, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 394)
    - Lecture notes for The Explainers: 1962 October 15, 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 395)
      Presented by Pamela and Livingston Gearhart at the Buffalo Museum of Science Music in action lecture series.
  - Awards, 1972 April 14, V.E; Folder 396
    - Kiwanis Club of Buffalo award in recognition of outstanding service to youth in the field of music: 1972 April 14, 1 item (Box 6, Folder 396)
- Additional correspondence, 1962-2005, VI.; Folder 397-421
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Amherst Central School District (Amherst, N.Y.): 1997-1999, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 397)
    Correspondence related to the administration of the Livingston Gearhart Fund established by Pamela Gearhart.
  - Braun, Elaine: 1997 January 17, 1 leaf (Box 7, Folder 398)
  - Dillon-Krass, Jacquelyn: 1995 April 28, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 399)
    Written on behalf of the American String Teachers Association.
  - Fleck, William: 1995-1996, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 400)
  - Gall, Cornelius: 1989 April 14, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 401)
    Includes list of Pamela Gearhart's performances 1975-1988.
  - Gazda, Doris: 2001-2002, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 402)
  - Harbison, Sue: 1988 January 30, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 403)
    Label on envelope: Mr. and Mrs. G. Burton Harbison.
  - Herfurth, C. Paul (Clarence Paul), 1893-1988: 1976-1979, 6 leaves (Box 7, Folder 404)
    Correspondence to and from Herfurth regarding an arrangement by Livingston Gearhart.
  - Hosmer, Helen M.: 1983 December 9, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 405)
  - Jesselson, Robert: 2000 February 14, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 406)
    On letterhead for American String Teachers Association.
  - Laredo, Jaime: 2000 August 16, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 407)
  - Lucktenberg, Jerrie Cadek: 2001 November 13, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 408)
  - New England Conservatory of Music: 1979-1980, 2 items (Box 7, Folder 409)
  - New York State School Music Association: 1983 March 21, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 410)
    Contract to rehearse All-State string orchestra.
  - Scherer Alfee, Martha: 2003, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 411)
  - Scott, Susan: 2005 April 16, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 412)
  - Shapiro, Eudice: 2003 March 10, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 413)
  - Shawnee Press: 1977-1983, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 414)
    Correspondence to and from representatives of Shawnee Press.
  - Sorel, Claudette, 1932-1999: 1978 March 17, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 415)
    Written on behalf of the New York State Federation of Music Clubs.
  - Storch, Laila: 2002-2003, 2 items (Box 7, Folder 416)
  - Syracuse Camerata: 1988-1990, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 417)
  - University at Buffalo: 1962-1979, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 418)
    Correspondence and appointment documents from personnel at the University at Buffalo.
  - Vamos, Almita: 2002 October 28, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 419)
  - Villa Maria Institute of Music (Buffalo, N.Y.): 1964-1967, 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 420)
    Consists of contracts.
  - Zaninelli, Luigi: 2002 May 21, 1 item (Box 7, Folder 421)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Gearhart, Livingston
Subjects
Women conductors (Music)--New York (State); Women violinists--New York (State); Gearhart, Pamela--Archives; Gerhart, Russell, 1902-1972
Genres
Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Programs (documents)
Associated Material
Separated Material
Thirty photographs received with the collection were removed to form a separate collection. It was later expanded to include 207 photographs.
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Pamela Gearhart Photograph Collection, 1957-1997
Mus. Arc. 33.1
The collection contains 207 photographs, including images of Russell, Gerhart, Franco Autori, Claudette Sorel, Edward Murphy, Mischa Mischakoff, Livingston Gearhart, Alexander and Mischa Schneider, Skitch Henderson, and Pamela Gearhart.
Livingston Gearhart Papers, 1933-1997
Mus. Arc. 23.1
The collection contains prose writings, vitae, correspondence, teaching materials, programs, and clippings.
Livingston Gearhart Recordings, 1949-2001
Mus. Arc. 23.4
The collection contains reel to reel and cassette tapes, compact discs, and LPs containing music composed or arranged by Livingston Gearhart.